CURRICULUM-VITAE

Vijay Aithekar

HOD (Applied Physics dept.)

Jayoti Vidhyapeeth Women's University (JVWU), Jaipur

(NAAC A+, and 12B approved university)

283-Pragati Nagar, Near Rajendra Nagar,

Indore (m.p.).

Mobile No – (9827633683,9340849827)

Email: vijayaithekar@ gmail.com



Objective

"Defining teaching as facilitating learning implies that while considerations of knowledge transfer are no doubt important, they are valuable only in relation to the quality of learning that they trigger."

To evolve as a good academician and to emerge as a visible and effective teacher and researcher, in the field of **Teaching.**

Present Status (Total 14 years of Exp.) International Publication. - (13) National – (04)

Working as **Associate Professor** (**HOD**) in (Applied Physics) Dept., at **Jayoti Vidhyapeeth** Women's University (JVWU) [NAAC A+ and 12B Approved university], Jaipur (Rajasthan) from (2017 to till Date)

Professional Experiences

➤ 4 years teaching experience as a Associate Professor (HOD) in (Applied Physics & HS)

Dept. at Mandsuar Institute of Technology, Indore from (2013 to 2017).

- ➤ 3 years teaching experience as a Assistant Professor in (Applied Physics & ECE Dept.) at Venkteshwar Institute of Technology (VIT) Indore (m.p.) from (2010 to 2013).
- > 5 months teaching experience as a Assistant Professor (Visiting) in (Applied Physics Dept.) at Sanghvi Innovative Academy (SIA) Indore (m.p.).
- ➤ 3 years teaching experience as a Assistant Professor (HOD) in (Applied Physics & ECE) Dept. at BM College of Technology (BMCT), Indore (m.p.) from (2007 to 2010).

Educational Qualification

- > PHD Physics (Pursuing)
- ➤ Master of Technology (M.Tech.) in (Eng. Physics & Opto-Electronics) with specialization in electronics & communication (ECE) from Shri Govindram Seksariya Institute of Technology & Science (SGSITS), Indore with first division 64.00 % (2007).
- ➤ Master of Philosophy (M.Phil.) in Eng. Physics (Applied Physics) with first Division (73.92%) in 2009.
- Master of Science (M.Sc.) in Eng. Physics (Applied Physics) with specialization in Lasers and fiber optics form Shri Govindram Seksariya Institute of Technology & Science (SGSITS), Indore, with first division 66% (2005).
- Master of Business Administration (M.B.A.) in HRM (with specialization in Human Resource Management MIT Institute, Indore, with first division 76 % division (2012).
- ➤ Bachelor of Science (**B.Sc.**) in PCM from Devi Ahilya Vishwavidhyalya (**D.A.V.V**) with 53% (2003).
- ➤ High secondary (12th) with PCM from Trilok Chandra Jain H. S. School Indore, (M.P. Board Bhopal) with (2000).

➤ High School (10th) with Science from Trilok Chandra Jain H. S. School Indore, (M.P. Board Bhopal) in (1998).

Course Taught at UG & PG level (B.Tech, B.E. M.Tech., M.Sc., M.Phil., M.B.A., Diploma)

Eng. Physics	Urses Optical communication Eng.
Lasers Physics	Relativity and Quantum Mechanics
Optical Networking	Nano electronics (NE)
Digital electronics (DE)	Basic Electronics & Electrical Eng. (BEEE).
Electronics devices and Circuit (EDC)	Electronics and Instrumentation (IM)
Digital Communication system (DCS)	Electricity and Electromagnetism
Classical Mechanics (M.Sc.)	Statistical Mechanics (M.Sc.)
Quantum Mechanics (M.Sc.)	Principle and practice of Management (POM)
Electronics and Electricals materials(EEM)	Applied Physics (B.Tech level)
Atomic, Molecular, nuclear and solid state Physics	Electronics and Electricals materials(EEM)
Basic theory of Computer	

Responsibilities Handled

➤ Working Academic Head and HOD (Physics and Applied Science Dept.) at **Jayoti** Vidhya Peeth Women's University (JVWU), Jaipur (Rajasthan).

- ➤ As an **HOD** of (Physics Dept.) also Electronics & Communication Engineering (**ECE**) handled, Time Table setup, Syllabus distribution, and innovation in the subject.
- ➤ Handled Academic Head, HOD, First Year In charge, Coordinator work.
- ➤ Handled Library In charge and Library Verification work.
- ➤ Handled Exam Dept. at MIT Indore, VIT Indore, BMCT institute of technology Indore (M.P.).

Professional Membership

- Awarded active Professional membership from **Institute of Engineering Research and Publication (IFERP)** from 13-06-2020 to Life time for Research and Publication.
- Achieve the Editorial board and Reviewer membership from International Journal of Creative Research Thoughts (IJCRT) e- ISSN: 2320-282.
- Member of International Association of Computer Science and Information Technology (IACSIT).

Training & Workshop Participation

Participated AICTE National level One Week Short Term Training Program on "Matlab-Statistics And Data Science" Organized By Dept. Of Applied Science Held at Sagar Institute of Research and Technology, BHOAPL on February 27 July to 1 August 2020.

National & International Workshop and Conferences Participation

Member of Organizing Committee in National Workshop on "Recent Advances in Teaching Methodology & Education Development II (RATMED -II)" held at Jayoti Vdyapeeth Women's University (JVWU), Jaipur, from 10 April 12 April 2019.

- ➤ Participated In "International Conference on Materials for Energy Application "Held at S.S. Jain Subodh P.G. College, Jaipur, and 6-8 Dec. 2018.
- Participated In International conference on "Advancement of Interdisciplinary Research (INCAIR2020)", Organized by Dept. Of Applied Science at Sagar Institute of Research and Technology, Bhopal from 22 July 2020.
- ➤ Member of organizing committee in **National workshop** on "**Recent Trends in Nanotechnology (RTN)**" held at SGSITS, Indore, and 29 march to 31march 2007.
- Also Participated Intentional level work shop on "NATIONAL LASERSYMPOSIUM (NLS-6)" held at Raja Ramana Center for Advance Technology (RRCAT) Indore (M.P.), 5-8 December 2006.
- Participated National level work shop on "Semiconductor Science And Technology" held at Sapthagiri College of Engineering Bengaluru, 12-14 June 2020.
- Participated National level work shop on "Awareness of Intellectual Property Rights and Training Program" held at Shri Ratanlal Patni Girls College, Kishangargh, 30 March 2019.
- Participated National level conference on "Resilience And Resource Management including ICT For sustainable Agriculture & Biotechnology" Held at D.R. M.P.S. Groups of Instaurations, AGRA on February 23-24 -2019.
- ➤ Participated International level Conference on "Recent Researches and Innovations in Sciences, Management, Education and Technology" Held at JCD PG College of Education Haryana on 27-28 March 2018.

Seminar Participation

➤ Participated Online National level Seminar on "Effective Time Management" Held at Ashoka Institute of Technology And Management, Varanasi on 01 June 2020.

- ➤ Participated Online National level Seminar on "Two Hands of Stress Management" Held at SAGE University, Indore (m.p.) on 31 July 2020.
- ➤ Attended National Level Higher & Technical Education Conclave, North India 2020 Held at North India , Organized by Elets Education on 24 July 2020.

Best Achievements and Publication during Academic Duty

- Achieve Best Professor Award At National Conference on "Resilience And Resource Management including ICT For sustainable Agriculture & Biotechnology" Held at D.R. M.P.S. Groups of Instaurations, AGRA on February 23-24-2019.
- Achieve Academic Excellence Award At National Conference on Recent Advances in Teaching Methodology & Education Development II (RATMED -II)" held at Jayoti Vdyapeeth Women's University (JVWU), Jaipur, from 10 April 12 April 2019.
- Achieve **Best Innovation Idea Award** at Zero Investment for Innovations for Education Initiatives (A Platform for teachers, by the Teachers" held at ZIIEI association With HDFC Bank. Form 11 March 2020.
- ➤ One Research Publication on "Study of Nonlinear Absorption in Pure and Mg doped Lithium Niboate crystals samples" in National Conference on "Resilience And Resource Management including ICT For sustainable Agriculture & Biotechnology" Held at D.R. M.P.S. Groups of Instaurations, AGRA on February 23-24-2019

Faculty Development Program (FDP) Participation

Attended National Faculty Development Program (FDP) on "Effective Teaching Methodology & IT Tools" and achieve Certificate of Appreciation held at Jayoti Vidyapeeth Women's University (JVWU), Jaipur Rajasthan. 10-11 Feb 2019.

- Attended 3 Days National Faculty Development Program (FDP) on "Recent Trends in Technology & Teaching Learning Methodology" and achieve Certificate of Appreciation held at SAGE University Indore. 09-11 July 2020 Association with Indian Society For Technical Education.
- Participated 7 Days National Faculty Development Program (FDP) on "Recent Trends in Management" and achieve Certificate of Appreciation held at GATES Institutes of Technology Andhra Pradesh. From 13-07-2020 to 19-07-2020 Association with Indian Society for Technical Education.
- Attended 3 Days National Faculty Development Program (FDP) on "Recent Trends in Technology & Teaching Learning Methodology" and achieve Certificate of Appreciation held at SAGE University Indore. 09-11 July 2020 Association with Indian Society For Technical Education.
- Attended 2 Days International Faculty Development Program (IFDP) on "Business Education & Pedagogy: Dimension & Future" and achieve Certificate of Appreciation held at SAGE University Indore. 17-18 July 2020 Association with Indian Society for Technical Education.

Webinar Participations

➤ Participated National level Webinar on "Let's Talk about Covid 19" held at APEX University Jaipur Association with External Hospital Jaipur, 12 June 2020.

Courses

- Attended National level Webina "Importance of Skill Education and Entrepreneship BSDU Model" held at BSDU University Jaipur, 02 June 2020.
- Participated National level Webinar on "Emerging Diplomatic Border issues of India & Its Neighborhood" held at ISBM University Chhattisgarh Organized School of Arts and HS IBSM, 15 June 2020.

- Participated National level Webinar on "Emerging Diplomatic Border issues of India & Its Neighborhood" held at ISBM University Chhattisgarh Organized School of Arts and HS IBSM, 15 June 2020.
- ➤ Participated International level Webinar on "Knowledge Sharing on A to Z of Journal Publication" Organized IFERP Research and Publication, 30 May 2020.
- ➤ Participated International level Webinar on "Research Article Writing and Publishing in Good Impact Journal" Organized Institute of Engineering Research & Publication (IFERP), 13 June 2020.
- ➤ Participated International level Webinar on "Virtual Interactive Classroom For Teachers and challenging Technology in Post Covid19 Era" Organized By (IFERP), 05 June 2020.
- Participated National level Webinar on "Post Covid Life Management" Organized By IES University, Bhopal, 11 July 2020.
- Participated National level Webinar on "Leaders in Action" Organized by IES University, Bhopal, 10 July 2020.
- ➤ Participated National level Webinar on "Leaders in Action" Organized By **IES University**, Bhopal, 10 July 2020.
- Participated National level Webinar on "Aspect of Scientific Research in Management".
 Organized by ANAND Institute of Management, Bhopal, 10 July 2020.

Online Quiz Participations

➤ Participated in National Online Quiz on "Gender Equality Awarness" Organized By Anjuman Arts, Science, Commerce & PG Studies, Darwad, From 22 to 24 July 2020.

Courses

Participated in International Online Quiz on "COVID 19 Awareness Quiz 2020" Organized By Rajiv Gandhi Central University, Arunachal Pradesh, 01 August 2020.

- Participated National level online Quiz on "Atmanibahar BHARAT" Organized By BSDU University, Jaipur, 04 June 2020.
- Participated online Quiz on "COVID -19 COMBATANT" Organized By Vinayaka Mission Research Foundation, 18 May 2020.
- ➤ Participated online Quiz on "Mobile Communication" Organized by Dept. of ECE, Pune Vidyarthi Griha's College of Engineering Nashik, 07 Jan. 2020.
- ➤ Participated online Quiz on "Online Quizophile 2020 Competition" Organized by ECG College of Engineering, 15 May 2020.

LIST OF INTERNATIONAL PUBLICATIONS

- [1] Author: Vijay Aithekar., "An Research Article on Fabrication and Characterization of Nickel Oxide Coated Solar Cell"., Volume 3 Issue 5, August 2019. International Journal of Trend in Scientific Research and Development (IJTSRD),e- ISSN: 2456 6470.
- [2] Author: Vijay Aithekar., "A Research Review Article on Journey of A Star: From Begining to End"., Volume 3 Issue 5, August 2019. International Journal of Trend in Scientific Research and Development (IJTSRD),e- ISSN: 2456 6470.
- [3] Author: Vijay Aithekar, Dr. Sangeeta Gautam., "A Research Article on Synthesis of Metal Nano Particles by Chemical Reduction Method"., Volume 3 Issue 5, August 2019., International Journal of Trend in Scientific Research and Development (IJTSRD), e-ISSN: 2456 6470.
- [4] Author: Vijay Aithekar, Dr. Sangeeta Gautam., "An Review Article on Radioactive Pollution"., Volume 3 Issue 5, August 2019., International Journal of Trend in Scientific Research and Development (IJTSRD), e-ISSN: 2456 6470.
- [5] Author: Vijay Aithekar., "A Review of Metal Organic Chemical Vapor Deposition (MOCVD) Technique". Vol. 5(2), June 2019: 1-7., Annals of Natural Sciences, e-ISSN: 2455-667X.
- [6] Author: Vijay Aithekar,. "A Review on Different Types of Solar Cells and Their Characteristics"., Vol. 5(2), June 2019: 1-7., Annals of Natural Sciences, e-ISSN: 2455-667X.

[7] Author: Vijay Aithekar, Dr. Vishal Saxana., "Experimental Study of Third Order Nonlinear Absorption in Pure and MG Doped Lithium Niobate Crystals". Volume 3 Issue 6, October 2019. International Journal of Trend in Scientific Research and Development (IJTSRD e-ISSN: 2456 – 6470.

Conference Publication

- > One Research Publication on "Role of Solar Photovoltaic Technology in development of Social Work" in International Conference on "Advancement of Interdisciplinary Research (INCAIR2020)", Organized by Dept. Of Applied Science at Sagar Institute of Research and Technology, Bhopal from 22 July 2020.
- ➤ Research Publication on "Study of Nonlinear Absorption in Pure and Mg doped Lithium Niboate crystals samples" in National Conference on "Resilience And Resource Management including ICT For sustainable Agriculture & Biotechnology" Held at D.R. M.P.S. Groups of Instaurations, AGRA on February 23-24 -2019.

COMPUTER LITERACY

➤ **PLATFORMS** : MS-DOS, Windows 98/2000/XP, MS-Office 2000.

LANGUAGES : C, C+, Labview 8.0, FORTRAN, Optiwave 8.0,

Origin 4.0, Mathcad 4.0.

PROJECT UNDERTAKEN

1. ORGANIZATION : Shri Govindram Seksariya Institute of Technology &

Science, Indore.

PROJECT TITLE : "Single Beam Z-scan Measurement technique of Third

order Nonlinearity with Lab views 8.0 automation".

TOOL : Lab view 8.0, Origin 6.0.

CLASS : M.Tech

GUIDED BY : **Dr.** (**Prof.**) **P.K. Sen**, Professor and Head SGSITS, and Indore

2. ORGANIZATION : Shri Govindram Seksariya Institute of Technology &

Science (SGSITS), Indore.

PROJECT TITLE : "Second order Nonlinearity in Polyazomethine ether and

Characterization."

DURATION : 6 Months.

MOTIVE : To study Synthesized Polyazomethine ether and find out

Second- Order Nonlinearity and characterized polyazomethine

Eather.

TOOL : Origin 8.0. Origin 6.0.

GUIDED BY : **Dr.** (**Prof.**) **P.K. Sen**, Professor and Head SGSITS, and Indore,

Dr. (Mrs.) Pratima Sen, Professor D.A.V.V., Indore.

Class : M.Sc.

3. ORGANIZATION: Shri Govindram Seksariya Institute of Technology &

Science (SGSITS) Indore

PROJECT TITLE : "A Review of MOCVD technique".

CLASS : M.Tech

DURATION : 6 Months.

EXTRA CO-CURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

- Actively Participated in M.P. level Taekwondo championships in (1999).
- Participated in second Indore District Taekwondo Championships held at Indore.
- Member of laky wonder Taekwondo club Indore.
- Participated in Various Dramas, stage and playing competitions in school level and college level.

Participated and Achieve International Yoga Day Certification from Heart fullness Society.

Student Supervision (Project thesis Guidance)

M.Tech: 1 (Ongoing) on the topic of "Two Degree Freedom Control Scheme for Open Loop Unstable with Time Delay Process as a Guides

M.Sc (Physics): Guided 10 M.Sc. Research Project. At JVWU University Jaipur.

B.Tech: 10 (Ongoing) on the topic of "Identification of integrating and unstable processes from relay feedback" & "On-line computing of PI/lead compensators for industry processes with gain and phase specifications" as a main Guide.

Personal Information

Name : Vijay Aithekar.

D.O.B : 10th-june-1984.

Father's name : Mr. Ramesh Chandra Aithekar.

Mother's name : Mrs. Sarla Aithekar

Languages known: English, Hindi, Marathi.

Martial Status : Married Courses

E-mail : vijayaithekar@gmail.com, vijayaithekar@rediffmail.com

Mobile No : +919827633683, 9340849827

References

(1) Mr. Ashutosh Aithekar

Asst. Professor
Department of Mathematics
SD Bansal College of Technology Indore
M.P. 452012

ashu_aithekar @yaoo.co.in,

Mobile No: 9977689055

(2) Mr. Prasad R Gokhale

Assistant Professor

Department of Chemistry
Malwa Inst. Of Tech. Indore
IndiaM.P. 452012 IndiaE-mail:

Mobile No: +919826256061

Courses Taught

Declaration

I hereby declare that all the information given above are true to the best of my knowledge and belief.

Date: Taught

Place: Indore (M.P.) (VIJAY AITHEKAR)